{"test_questions": [[{"question": "In the following non planar graph number of independent loop equations are", "opta": "8", "optb": "12", "optc": "7", "optd": "5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of independent loop equations are given by, \nL = B - N + 1\nwhere L : No. of loop equations\nB : No. of branches = 12\nN : No. of nodes = 8\nL = 12 - 8 + 1 = 5."}, {"question": "A transmission line has a characteristic impedance of 50 \u03a9 and a resistance of 0.1 \u03a9/m, if the line is distortion less, the attenuation constant (in Np/m) is", "opta": "500", "optb": "5", "optc": "0.014", "optd": "0.002", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Distortion less \na = RG and Z0 = RG \u2192 \n."}, {"question": "A certain 8 bit uniform quantization PCM system can accommodate a signal ranging from - 1 V to + V. The rms value of the signal is V . The signal to quantization noise ratio is:", "opta": "30 dB", "optb": "46.91 dB", "optc": "40 dB", "optd": "49.92 dB", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(SNR)dB = 1.76 + 6.02n\nn = 8\nThus (SNR)dB = 1.76 + 6.02 x 8 = 49.92 dB."}, {"question": "A rectangular waveguide, in dominant TE mode, has dimensions 10 cm x 15 cm. The cut off frequency is", "opta": "10 GHz", "optb": "1 GHz", "optc": "15 GHz", "optd": "25 GHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For TE10 mode"}, {"question": "A radar receiver has a noise figure of 10 dB at 300 K having a bandwidth of 2.5 MHz. The minimum power it can receive is", "opta": "3.45 x 10-15 W", "optb": "1.38 x 10-15 W", "optc": "7.5 x 10-15 W", "optd": "93.15 x 10-15 W", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Pm = kT0\u0394f(F - 1) = 93.15 x 10-15 W."}, {"question": "In the circuit shown, in switch S is open for a long time and is closed at t = 0. The current i(t) for t \u2265 0+ is", "opta": "i(t) = 0.5 - 0.125e-1000t A", "optb": "i(t) = 1.5 - 0.125e-1000t A", "optc": "i(t) = 0.5 - 0.5e-1000t A", "optd": "i(t) = 0.375e-1000t A", "ans": "A", "explanation": "i(f) = 0.5, i(i) = 0.75\ni(t) = Vr + (ii - ij)e-1/p = 0.5 - 0.125e-1000t ."}, {"question": "In a semiconductor material. The hole concentration is found to be 2 x 2.5 x 1015 cm-3. If mobility of carriers is 0.13 m2/ v-s. Then find the current density if electric field intensity is 3.62 x 10-19", "opta": "7.6237 x 10-4 A/cm2", "optb": "7.6237 x 10-5 A/cm2", "optc": "7.6237 x 10-3 A/cm2", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Current density J = \u03c3E \nWhere \u03c3 = conductivity \nGiven -> \u03bc = 0.13 m2/v-s = 0.13 x 104 cm2/V sec \nP = 2.25 x 1015/cm3 \nWe have, \u2234 ni = 1.5 x 1010 \nAlso n.p. = \n\u2234 n = /p \n \n \n= (1.6 x 10-19 x 0.13 x 104 x 2.25 x 1015) x \n= (0.468) (4.5 x 1015) \n\u03c3 = 2.106 x 1015 \u03bc/cm \nJ = \u03c3E \n\u2234 Current density = 2.106 x 1015 x 3.620 x 10-19 \n= 7.6237 x 10-4 A/m2."}, {"question": "Consider the system  with  and where p and q are arbitrary real numbers. Which of the following statements about the controllability of the system is true?", "opta": "The system is completely state controllable for any non zero values p and q", "optb": "Only p = 0 and q = 0 result in controllability", "optc": "The system is uncontrollable for all values of p and q", "optd": "We cannot conclude about controllability from the given data", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Use the condition of controllability."}, {"question": "A MOSFET has a threshold voltage of 1 V and oxide thickness of 500 x 10-8 [\u03b5r = 3.9; \u03b50 = 8.85 x 10-14 F/cm, q = 1.6 x 10-19 c]. The region under the gate is ion implanted for threshold voltage tailoring. The base and type of impant required to shift threshold voltage to - 1 V are __________ .", "opta": "8.6 x 1011/cm2, p-type", "optb": "8.6 x 1011/cm2, n-type", "optc": "0.86 x 109/cm2, p-type", "optd": "1.02 x 1012/cm2, n-type", "ans": "A", "explanation": "VT(new) = VT(odd) +\n \n= 6.903 x 10-8 \n\u2234  \n\u2234  \nfB = - 8.6 x 1011 \nThe threshold voltage is always negative for p-channel and hence implant is of p-type."}, {"question": "What is the propagation constant for air filled wave guide with dimensions a = 1.59\" and b = 0.795\" at 4.95 GHz?", "opta": "0.6698", "optb": "0.7698", "optc": "0.503", "optd": "0.6598", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Here, \na = 1.59'' = 40.386 mm = 4.04 cm\n\u2234 ."}, {"question": "Radiation resistance of an antenna is 54 &ohm; and loss resistance is 6 &ohm;. If antenna has power gain of 10, then directivity is:", "opta": "9", "optb": "11.11", "optc": "data not sufficient", "optd": "10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Efficiency of antenna \n\nPower gain = 10\n\nThus directivity ."}, {"question": "If the power spectral density of stationary random process is a sine-squared function of frequency, the shape of its autocorrelation is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since autocorrelation function and power spectral density bears a Fourier transform relation, then since required in frequency domain will five rectangular convolutions in time domain thus it is triangular function."}, {"question": "The inverse of given Laplace transform is", "opta": "sin t", "optb": "cos t", "optc": "et", "optd": "e2t", "ans": "B", "explanation": "s = x2 - ex\n\nx(t) = cos t."}, {"question": "Consider the amplitude modulated (AM) signal Ac cos \u03c9ct + 2 cos \u03c9mt cos \u03c9ct For demodulating the signal using envelope detector, the minimum value of Ac should be", "opta": "2", "optb": "1", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "AC cos \u03c9ct + 2 cos \u03c9mt cos \u03c9ct\nAC cos\u03c9ct\nfor envelope detection \u03bc < 1 &Rightarrow;  < 1 &Rightarrow; Ac should be at least-2."}, {"question": "In a 4 bit weighted resistor D/A converter, the resistor value corresponding to LSB is 32 k\u03a9. The resistor value corresponding to MSB will be", "opta": "32 K\u03a9", "optb": "16 K\u03a9", "optc": "8 K\u03a9", "optd": "4 K\u03a9", "ans": "D", "explanation": "2n - 1 R = 32 K&Omeg;\nn = 4\n&Rightarrow; 8R = 32\nR = 4 K\u03a9."}, {"question": "Find 'X' in the circuit below :f1(A, B, C, D) = \u03a3(6, 7, 13, 14);f2(A, B, C, D) = \u03a3(3, 6, 7);f3(A, B, C, D) = \u03a3(5, 6, 7, 14, 15)", "opta": "p(0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 15)", "optb": "0", "optc": "\u03a3(14)", "optd": "1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "f1(A, B, C, D) = \u2211(6, 7, 13, 14)\nf2(A, B, C, D) = \u2211(3, 6, 7)\nf1 \u2295 f2 = \u2211(3, 13, 14)\nf3 x (f1 \u2295 f2) = \u2211(14) = y\nX = f1 x y &Rightarrow; \u221114."}, {"question": "Suppose that the modulating signal is m(t) = 2cos (2pfmt) and the carrier signal is xC(t) = AC cos(2pfct), which one of the following is a conventional AM signal without over modulation?", "opta": "x(t) = Acm(t)cos(2pfct)", "optb": "x(t) = Ac [1 + m(t)]cos (2pfct)", "optc": "", "optd": "x(t) = Accos(2pfmt)cos(2pfct) + Acsin(2pfmt)sin(2pfct)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(C) is without over modulation."}, {"question": "What are the values of Emax and Emin displayed on the oscilloscope, when a 1 kV P-P carries is modulated to 50%?", "opta": "2 kV, 0.5 kV", "optb": "1 kV, 0.5 kV", "optc": "0.75 kV, 0.25 kV", "optd": "0.5 kV, 1.5 kV", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Emax - Emin = 0.5 x 1 kV = 0.5 kV\n2Emax = 1.5 kVi, Emax = 0.75 kV\nEmin = 0.25 kV."}, {"question": "Consider the common emitter amplifier shown below with the following circuit parameters: \u03b2 = 100, gm = 0.3861 A/V, r0 = \u221e rp = 259 \u03a9, Rs = 1 k\u03a9, RB = 93 k\u03a9, RC = 250 \u03a9, RL = 1 kW, C1 = \u221e and C2 = 4.7mF.The resistance seen by the source Vs is", "opta": "258 \u03a9", "optb": "1258 \u03a9", "optc": "93 k\u03a9", "optd": "\u221e", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Zs = Rs + (RB || Brs)\nrc = 2.475 = 1.258 kV"}, {"question": "As the temperature increases the mobility of electrons __________ .", "opta": "decreases because the number of carries increases with increased collisions", "optb": "increases because the number of carries decreases with decreased collisions", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Mobility of electrons \nm = 2.5 for electrons and 2.7 for holes in Si."}, {"question": "Consider the following Maximum energy of electrons liberated photoelectrically is independent of light intensityMaximum energy of electrons liberated photoelectrically varies nonlinearly with frequency of incident light.", "opta": "(1) is true and (2) is false", "optb": "(1) and (2) both are true", "optc": "(1) is false and (2) is true", "optd": "(1) and (2) both are false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Statement (ii) is false because maximum energy of photons varies linearly with frequency of incident light. It can be shown as follows : \n \nF1 > F2 > F3 \nj = light intensity = constant \nPhotocurrent Vs Anode voltage with frequency and incident light as a parameter. \nThe light intensity is constant."}, {"question": "When phase-lag compensation is used in a system, then gain cross over frequency, bandwidth and undamped frequency are respectively", "opta": "Increased, Increased, Increased", "optb": "Increased, Increased, Decreased", "optc": "Increased, Decreased, Decreased", "optd": "Decreased, Decreased, Decreased", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Phase lag is delay between a correcting signal of control system and response to it."}, {"question": "The equivalent form of the logical expression ABC + A BC + ABC + ABC + AB C is", "opta": "C + (A \u2295 B)", "optb": "(A + B + C)(A + B + C)", "optc": "(A + B + C)(A + B + C)(A + B + C)", "optd": "(A + B + C)(A + B + C)(A + B + C)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "This can be solve by using Boolean identity but using k map it will be more easy\n\n(A + B + C) (A + B + C) (A + B + C)."}, {"question": "The gradient of any scalar field always yields __________ .", "opta": "a solenoidal field", "optb": "a conservative field", "optc": "an irrotational field", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Dot product is conservative. Gradient is nothing but dot product."}, {"question": "In a flash type ADC, employing 15 comparators resolution with 10 volts reference; is expected to be :", "opta": "0.625 V", "optb": "0.656 V", "optc": "0.525 V", "optd": "insufficient data", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since number of comparators = 2n - 1 = 15; \nThen number of bits are '4'\nResolution"}, {"question": "Consider the signal flow graph shown in figure below. The gain  is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "P1 = abcd\nL1 = be, L2 = cf, L3 = dg\n\u03941 = 1\n\n."}, {"question": "During transmission over a communicate channel, bit errors occur independently with probability . If a block of 3 bits are transmitted, the probability of at most one bit error is equal to", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Probability of no-error + probability one error\n\n."}, {"question": "If x1[n]  x1(z) with ROC = R1 and x2[n]  x2(z) with ROC = R2 then ROC for x1[n] + x2[n] will be __________ (where Ri \u2192 Region of convergence and x1[n] and x2[n] are causal).", "opta": "R1 \u2229 R2", "optb": "R1 \u222a R2", "optc": "(R1 \u222a R2) \u2229 (R1)", "optd": "(R1 \u2229 R2) \u222a (R1)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "R1 \u2229 R2, Suppose R1 for x1(n) be\n\nThen ROC for x1(n) + x2(n) \nR1 \u2229 R2 (R1 < R2)\nThen ROC for x1(n) + x2(n)\nR1 \u2229 R2(R1 < R2)"}, {"question": "Consider a unity feedback control system with open-loop transfer function  The steady state error of the system due to a unity step input is :", "opta": "zero", "optb": "K", "optc": "1/K", "optd": "infinite", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The analog signal given below is sampled at 1200 samples per second. m(t) = 2 sin 120 pt + 3 sin 240 pt + 4 sin 360 pt + 5 sin 480 pt + 6 sin 600 pt + 7 sin 720 pt. The folding (maximum) frequency is __________ .", "opta": "300 Hz", "optb": "360 Hz", "optc": "600 Hz", "optd": "480 Hz", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Folding frequency (max.) = = 600 Hz."}, {"question": "If the system T.F. is  The differential equation representing the system is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(s3 + 2s2 + 5s + 6)y(s) = (s2 + 4) x (s)\ns3y(s) + 2s2y(s) + 5sy(s) + 6y(s) = s2 x (s) + 4 x (s) \nReplacing s by  and y(s) by y(t) and x(s) by x(t) we get \ny(t) + 2y(t) + 5y(t) + 6y(t)\n = x(t) + 4x(t) \n + 2 + 5 + 6 =  + 4x \nThis is required differential equation."}, {"question": "In the circuit below, delay of the EXOR and ANDLogic gates are 20 \u03bcs and 10 \u03bcs respectively, then the wave y' and y (with initial condition y = 1) will be :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since y is at logic '1' initially, y' must be at logic '1'. \nAlso, one input of the EXOR gate is tied to zero therefore 'f' will be directly transferred to the output. \nThe logic gates will introduce gate delays which will lead to the answer ."}, {"question": "The antenna current of an AM transmitter is 8 A, when only the carrier is sent, but it increases to 8.93 A when the carrier is modulated by a single sine wave. Determine the antenna current when the percent of modulation changes to 0.8", "opta": "9.19 A", "optb": "9.91 A", "optc": "10.56 A", "optd": "8.61 A", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Ic = 8 A \nm = 0.8 \n\n \n= 8 x 1.149 = 9.19 A."}, {"question": "A noiseless 3 KHz channel can transmit binary at the rate __________ .", "opta": "12000 bps", "optb": "10000 bps", "optc": "6000 bps", "optd": "3000 bps", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Maximum data rate for noiseless channel is given by Nyquist Theorem \n= 2H log2 V bits/sec \nV - discrete levels (Here Binary i.e. 2) \nH - Bandwidth \n\u2234 Maximum data rate = 2H log2 V \n= 2(3 KHz) log2 2 = 2 x 3 x 103 x 1 \n= 6 x 103 = 6000 bps."}, {"question": "Find Vx Vy Vz", "opta": "Vx = -6 Vy = 3 Vz = -3", "optb": "Vx = -6 Vy = -3 Vz = 1", "optc": "Vx = 6 Vy = 3 Vz = 3", "optd": "Vx = 6 Vy = 1 Vz = 3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Apply Mesh analysis\n\nApply KVL to mesh 2\n-2 + Vy + 1 = 0\n\u2234 Vy = 1\nApply KVL to mesh 1\n\u2234 -8 + Vx + 2 = 0\n\u2234 Vx = 6 V\nApply KVL to mesh 3\n-1 + Vz -2 = 0\n\u2234 Vz = 3 V."}, {"question": "If x[n]  then the sequence x[n] is", "opta": "non-periodic", "optb": "periodic", "optc": "depends on n", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Consider \nNumber of samples per period = 10p\nThis is not a rational number. Hence signal is non periodic."}, {"question": "The impulse response and the excitation function of a linear time invariant causal system are shown in figure (a) and (b) respectively. The output of the system at t = 2 sec is equal to", "opta": "0", "optb": "2", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The area of the shaded region \n."}, {"question": "Consider a stable and causal system with impulse response h(t) and system function H(S). Suppose H(S) is rational, contains a pole at S = - 2, and does not have a zero at the origin. The location of all other poles and zero is unknown for each of the following statements. Let us determine whether statement is true or false. f[h(t) e-3t] convergesh(t) has finite durationH(s) = H(- s) Choose correct option.", "opta": "1 - True, 2 - False, 3 - True, 4 - False", "optb": "1 - False, 2 - False, 3 - False, 4 - True", "optc": "1 - False, 2 - False, 3 - False, 4 - False", "optd": "1 - True, 2 - can't say, 3 - True, 4 - can't say", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Statement 1 is false, since f{h(t)e3t} corresponds to the value of the Laplace transform of h(t) at s = 3. \nIf this converges, it implies that s = - 3 is in the ROC. \nA casual and stable system must always have its ROC to the right of all its poles. However, s = - 3 is not to the right of the pole at s = - 2. \nStatement 2 is false, because it is equivalent to stating that H(0) = 0. This contradicts the fact that H(s) does not have a zero at the origin. \nStatement 3 is false. If h(t) is of finite duration, then if its Laplace transform has any points in its ROC, ROC must be the entire s-plane. \nHowever, this is not consistent with H(s) having a pole at s = - 2. \nStatement 4 is false. If it were true, then H(s) has a pole at s = - 2, it must also have a pole at s = 2. \nThis is inconsistent with the fact that all the poles of a causal and stable system must be in the left half of the s-plane."}, {"question": "The specific gravity of tungsten is 13.8 and its atomic weight is 184.0 Assume that there are two free elements per atom. Then the Fermi level or characteristic energy for the crystal in eV will be", "opta": "8.95 eV", "optb": "-8.95 eV", "optc": "7.326 eV", "optd": "-7.326 eV", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A quantity of any substance equal to its molecular weight in grams is a mole of that substance contains the same number of molecules as one mole of any other substance. This Avogadro's number and equals 6.02 x 1023 molecules per mole. Thus\n\n\n \n= 9.03 x 1028 electrons/m3\nSince for tungsten the atomic and the molecular weights are the same. Therefore for tungsten \nEF = 3.64 x 10-19(\u03b7)2/3 \n= 3.64 x 10- 19(9.03 x 1028)2/3 \nEF = 7.326 eV."}, {"question": "An air-filled rectangular waveguide has dimensions 8cm x 10cm . The phase velocity of guided wave at frequency of 3 GHz for TE10 mode is", "opta": "1.5 x 108 m/s", "optb": "5.5 x 108 m/s", "optc": "3.46 x 108 m/s", "optd": "0.18 x 107 m/s", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2234 VP = 3.46 x 108 m/s."}, {"question": "For a = - 1, find the value of V2", "opta": "\u221e", "optb": "0", "optc": "V1", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "V1 = i1R1 + i2R2 \ni1 + ai1 = i2 \nV2 = i2R2\n\n\n \nPutting a = - 1 \n = 0 V."}, {"question": "A unity-feedback control system has the open loop transfer function . If the input system is a unit ramp, the steady state error will be", "opta": "0", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "2", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For a given voltage, four heating coils will produce maximum heat when connected", "opta": "all in parallel", "optb": "all in series", "optc": "with two parallel pairs in series", "optd": "one pair in parallel with the other two in series", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Denominator polynomial of a transfer function of certain network is: s3 + s2 + 2s + 24 Then the network is:", "opta": "stable", "optb": "oscillatory", "optc": "unstable", "optd": "depends on numerator polynomial", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Routh array\n\n\n\nThere is negative number present in first column. Thus network is unstable."}, {"question": "A TV picture is to be transmitted over a channel of 6 MHz bandwidth at a 35 dB S/N ratio. The capacity of the channel is", "opta": "50 Mbps", "optb": "100 Mbps", "optc": "36 Mbps", "optd": "72 Mbps", "ans": "D", "explanation": "W = B = Bandwidth\n\nC = 6 x 106 x 12 = 72 Mbps."}, {"question": "The ratio of the diffusion coefficient in a semiconductor has the units", "opta": "V-1", "optb": "em.V-1", "optc": "V.cm-1", "optd": "V.s", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Consider the probability density f(x) = ae-b|x| where x is a random variable whose allowable values range from x = - \u221e to x = + \u221e. P(1 \u2264 x \u2264 2)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "(e-b - e-2b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "P(x) =  ae-b|x|dx\nto get  apply aebxdx + ae-bxdx, \nwe get  = ."}, {"question": "The amplitude of a pair of composite sinusoidal signal y(n) = x1(n) + x2(n) with x1(n) = sin (5pn) x2(n) = 3 sin (5pn) is __________ .", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Amplitude = ."}, {"question": "The amplifier circuit shown below uses a silicon transistor. The capacitors Cc and CE can be assumed to be short at signal frequency and the effect of output resistance r0 can be ignored. If CE is disconnected from the circuit, which one of the following statements is TRUE?", "opta": "The input resistance Ri increases and the magnitude of voltage gain Av decreases", "optb": "The input resistance Ri decreases and the magnitude of voltage gain Av decreases", "optc": "Both input resistance Ri and the magnitude of voltage gain Av decrease", "optd": "Both input resistance Ri and the magnitude of voltage gain Av increase", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Given circuit after removing CE will behave as current-series feedback. \nOverall voltage gain will decrease as feedback signal comes into picture and since it is current-series feedback, input impedance increases."}, {"question": "A n-channel JFET has IDSS = 2 mA, Gate to source voltage VGS = - 2 V and trans-conductance is 0.5 mW then pinch-off voltage is __________ .", "opta": "- 2 V", "optb": "2 V", "optc": "- 4 V", "optd": "4 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2234  \n\u2234  = - 8VP - 16 \n\u2234  + 8VP + 16 = 0 \n\u2234 (VP + 4)2 = 0 \n\u2234 VP = -4 V."}]]}